<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A petition to the High Court of Parliament, in the behalfe of auncient and authentiqne [sic] authors, for the vniversall and perpetuall good of euery man and his posteritie: presented by Ioseph. Webbe, Dr. in Ph</title>
            <author>Webbe, Joseph.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1624</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 34 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 12 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A14866</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 25170</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S119584</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99854791</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99854791</idno>
            <idno type="VID">20235</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A14866)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 20235)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1015:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A petition to the High Court of Parliament, in the behalfe of auncient and authentiqne [sic] authors, for the vniversall and perpetuall good of euery man and his posteritie: presented by Ioseph. Webbe, Dr. in Ph</title>
                  <author>Webbe, Joseph.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 20 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1623 [i.e. 1624]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Requests a grant of a patent for 21 years for his method of teaching languages.</note>
                  <note>The imprint year is given according to Lady Day dating.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Latin language --  Study and teaching --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:20235:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:20235:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A PETITION TO THE HIGH COVRT OF PARLIAMENT, In the behalfe of auncient <hi>and authentique Authors,</hi> For the vniverſall and perpetuall good of euery man and his poſteritie:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Preſented</hi> by IOSEPH WEBBE, Dr. in Ph.</p>
            <p>Printed 1623.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="petition">
            <pb facs="tcp:20235:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:20235:2"/>
            <head>A PETITION TO THE HIGH COVRT OF PARLIAMENT, In the behalfe of auncient and authentique Authors, <hi>For the univerſall and perpetuall good of euery man and his poſteritie.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>ALiud eſt Grammaticè, aliud Latine loqui,</hi> is a diſtinction of a thouſand fiue hundred and fortie yeares ſtanding; the Author is <hi>Quin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilian;</hi> and his ſenſe is thus:</p>
            <p>There are two ſorts of Latine, whereof one is <hi>Grammar-Latine,</hi> and the other <hi>Latine-Latine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>Latine-Latine</hi> I meane ſuch as the beſt appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued Authors wrote, and left vs in their bookes and monuments of vſe and cuſtome.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Grammar-Latine</hi> I vnderſtand that Latine that we now make by Grammar rules: the firſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention of which rules, and their collection out of that cuſtome, and thoſe Authors, was, to make vs write and ſpeake ſuch Latine as that Cuſtome and thoſe Authors did; which was, <hi>Latine-Latine:</hi> but it ſucceeded not.</p>
            <p>Wherefore <hi>my Petition is</hi> to this high Court of Parliament, (not that Grammar ſhould be queſtio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:20235:3"/>in y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it is our old acquaintance, and hath a long time been a ledger here amongſt vs, on the behalfe of theſe Authors; but, conſidering it is not able to giue vs Authors Latine) <hi>that theſe Authors, whom we ſeeme to haue ſo much reſpected in our Schooles and Vniverſities, coming themſelues as it were in perſon, and offering to dwell amongſt vs, may to their deſerued honour and our deſired benefit, be now receiued, priui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged and admitted to tell their owne tales, and teach vs their owne Latine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This admittance of theirs, haue I theſe eighteen yeares contriued, and theſe fiue laſt yeares ſeriouſly ſolicited, and cannot as yet find any way to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe it, without manifeſt danger of ruining my ſelf and mine aſſiſtants, vnleſſe by fauour of this high and honorable Court <hi>I may be allowed father of mine owne children, and Author of mine owne works and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uentions: that is, that no man elſe may print them or im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port them nor any man teach Languages by that method that I propoſe, but ſuch as I thinke fitting; and that theſe priuiledges may continue for the ſpace of</hi> 21 <hi>yeares after the publication of euery booke of this nature that ſhall be publiſhed within the terme of yeares before ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified; with prohibition that no man ſhall hereafter, du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring that time, attempt the ſame way in any other Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor or Language, without my ſpeciall allowance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Herein I haue not onely had the gracious eare of his Maieſtie, but Prince like encouragement of his Highneſſe, the aſſent of many of the Nobility, and the fauourable deſires and wiſhes of ſome of the greateſt Scholars of this kingdome; but eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially of ſuch whoſe ends and priuate reſpects led
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:20235:3"/>them not to a preiudicate opinion concerning it.</p>
            <p>But whilſt this hopefull beginning engaged me with full ſayle to proſecute my firſt intention, I found in the very maine of my buſineſſe ſome ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret <hi>Remora,</hi> ſuddenly to ſtop my helpleſſe ſhip, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the winds of my deuotion thereunto blew very ſtrongly.</p>
            <p>Whereupon, not knowing who did hurt me, or what might helpe mee, I began to liſten partly to mine owne ſurmiſes, partly to what my friends ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpected, and partly to the mutterings of ſuch as were incredulous: for all theſe brought ſundry ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iections and demands; to which I made theſe fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing anſwers; moſt humbly ſubmitting both my ſelfe and them vnto the cenſure and definitiue ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of your Honorable Wiſedomes, whether I ſhall ſtop here and ſinke, for attempting to bring a benefit to your poſteritie, or ſet forward to effect what I pretended.</p>
            <p>The firſt <hi>obiection</hi> was,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> that it might be thought a great preſumption and arrogancie in me, to attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute ſo much vnto my ſelfe, as to ſet vpon a new<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found thing, that for ſo many ages and amongſt ſo infinite a number of learned men, was never hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to reflected on; and therefore much to be ſuſpected and demurr'd vpon.</p>
            <p>This obiection I anſwered in mine <hi>Appeale to Truth, in the Controuerſie betweene Art and Vſe,</hi> pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed (<hi>Anno</hi> 1622. and extant at the brazen Serpent in Pauls Church-yard) to ſhew the opinions of the graueſt Authors to this purpoſe: and firſt, what Grammarians thought one of another; then, what
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:20235:4"/>others thought of Grammarians and their Art; and laſtly, what way they approued of, to come to puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of language.</p>
            <p>This approued way go I, which in the genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie is theirs, and none of mine; nor is it new, in that it hath beene euer ſince ſpeaking was, which was long before Grammar, and is where no Gram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mar euer came, and therefore may and will ſubſiſt ſubſiſt without her. From whence it may be gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, that I am ſo far from being preſumptuous or arrogant in putting on ſo publick and ſo great a be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit, that I might rather haue been held negligent or envious in concealing it; eſpecially being a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſor of letters, and as it were one of the Parliament in the Common wealth of learning.</p>
            <p>The ſecond obiection was,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> that though the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall way by cuſtome and authoritie might be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timated by theſe Authors, yet I could not excuſe my ſelfe of preſumption in the courſe I tooke vnto it in particular.</p>
            <p>Whereunto I anſwered, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> any man might take the ground-work of this particular way fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>Cicero,</hi> who was the firſt that taught mee to divide the man, or body of ſpeech into the parts thereof &amp; knittings. I meane not thoſe eight ſorts of parts, whereof 4 are declined, 4 vndeclined, after the vulgar Gram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mar; but after <hi>Cicero's</hi> Grammar, into one ſort of parts, that is, into clauſes, which are vndeclined. Now if <hi>Cicero's</hi> Grammar, that conſiſts of one part of ſpeech, and that vndeclined, were not much ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſier than that of eight parts, and 4 declined; and ſhould not thereby rid vs of much labour, and to
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:20235:4"/>better purpoſe, I ſhould not be ſo ready to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace it. But, as for that which is built vpon this ground worke, for the peculiar vſe of euery man, and the bringing of that into act, which theſe graue men haue giuen vs hitherto but to contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plate: that (without preſumption) I call mine; as the pipe of lead calls the water which it conveyes to many ciſternes; alwayes acknowledging the waters of all true vnderſtanding to proceed onely from the eternall fountaine of all wiſedome my Creator.</p>
            <p>But ſeeming ſtill to doubt of the poſſibilitie thereof, they would often aske me:
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Are you ſure you know what you promiſe? Is it poſſible to learne Latine without a Grammar?</p>
            <p>Hereupon I ſhewed them <hi>Quintilians</hi> fore-allea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged diſtinction; and then, I replied thus: It is not poſſible to learne Grammar-Latin without Gram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mar; but it is poſſible to learne Latin-Latin (that is, the Latine that was in vſe amongſt the ancient Latines) without Grammar. And moreouer, I told them, that I thought, the way to write and ſpeake this laſt Latine, was the true way <hi>rectè ſcribendi at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que loquendi;</hi> elſe <hi>Cicero</hi> and his equals wrote not rightly. And I inferred, that if this be true, we muſt either pull out <hi>rectè,</hi> or put in <hi>Grammaticè,</hi> or vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar Grammar would haue but an imperfect defini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. For <hi>rectè ſcribendi atque loquendi ars,</hi> muſt run along with the cuſtome and vſe of ſpeaking that was obſerued by thoſe ancient-Authors: which, I muſt confeſſe, the vulgar Grammar aimeth at, or elſe it ſhould want all colour and authoritie: but
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:20235:5"/>
               <hi>Quintilian,</hi> &amp; that that's more then ten <hi>Quintilians,</hi> the very practiſe tels vs, it hitteth not the marke of writing rightly. God is my record. I ſpeake not this to depriue Grammar of her ſcholars, (for ſhe hath her own worth, and according vnto it ſhould be reſpected) but <hi>my humble Petition is, that the old authentick Authors and chiefe Lords of Language, our beſt and ſyncereſt friends, may not be thruſt out of their owne patrimonie, by thoſe whoſe chiefest grace it is to be thought their followers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>They replyed:
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Suppoſe that we will grant you, that <hi>Authors-Latine</hi> is better then <hi>Grammar-Latine,</hi> what proofes bring you that it is poſſible for you to help vs to a way to learne this better Latin; that we may be aſſured that you can be as good as your promiſe?</p>
            <p>Whereunto I againe made anſwer: If I lay my grounds in that wherein all the Languages of the world agree, and out of which no Languages haue perfect correſpondence, and vpon theſe grounds and foundations can erect a ſolid and compleate edifice, doubtleſſe it will be poſſible for me to help you to that way, whereby I may performe what I haue promiſed. And proceeding yet further, I told them, that the grounds of ſpeech are laid in things, in the meanings of which things all tongues meet. Therefore as they are all the meanings of things, ſo they are all the meanings of one another. But if we will ſearch vnto the depth for the rootes and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lements of all theſe meanings, we ſhall finde that fartheſt off they conſiſt all in a point; a little nearer in a point, and in a right &amp; crooked line; yet nearer
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:20235:5"/>in literall characters produced of theſe point and lines; and nearer yet, in ſyllables produced of theſe letters: and yet ſomewhat nearer, in words produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced of theſe ſyllables. And vpon this ground of words, all ordinary wayes inſiſt.</p>
            <p>But they are not yet come to that which they pretend; for no two languages in the world doe perpetually and infallibly meete in words: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we muſt go yet a ſtep further, till we come at <hi>our foundation, which is layd in ſenſe or meaning;</hi> which conſiſteth not alwayes of ſimple words, but now of ſimple, now compoſed. For, as letters that are knit together, make one character of this or that word: ſo words knit together, make one character of this or that ſenſe. Theſe characters of ſenſe are <hi>the neareſt elements of ſpeech,</hi> vnderſtandingly ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged by <hi>Cicero</hi> vnder the names of ioynts and members; and are delivered vnto vs in their natiue formes and ſubſtances by Cuſtome and Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie. But Art amazed at the not well appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended, or ill diſtinguiſhed magnitude of this ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, matter or body of ſpeech, preſuming of her owne abilitie of bringing vs a nearer way to Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guages, hath taken both matter and formes thereof, &amp; torne them all in peeces: of the formes ſhe hath made a Grammar; of the matter a Dictionarie: and hath diſperſed them amongſt all nations for their ſeuerall vſes in forreine languages. And now, euery nation deſirous of a forrein tongue, runs preſently to Art to borrow theſe peeces, and thinkes by her inſtruction to compoſe a perfect and well ſhaped body of ſpeech in ſome deſired forreine language.
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:20235:6"/>But they are deceiued: for firſt, though Art know what ſimilar parts (as wee terme them) as, what nerves, films, fleſh, bones, &amp;c. euery inſtrumentall member conſiſteth of; yet, ſhe being vniuerſall for all nations, and all nations naturally varying the ſituation and poſition of theſe peeces or particles of members, according to their owne natiue Idiom; they muſt (as not taught by Art any other varia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) lay all theſe peeces of forreine ſpeech, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the ſituation of theſe peeces in their owne language. Whereupon, not to runne into <hi>France</hi> or <hi>Italy</hi> for an example, a Welch-man, not yet well grounded in our tongue, (ſpeaking <hi>Welch-Engliſh</hi>) bids vs here in England, giue him bread white, and meate fat, after the native poſition of theſe peeces of ſpeech in his language, and is laught at for his labour. In like maner an Engliſh man in Wales ſpeakes <hi>Engliſh-Welch,</hi> and bids giue him <hi>gwin barra</hi> and <hi>braſekige,</hi> that is, white bread and fat meate, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter his poſition of theſe peeces, and is as much laught at there, as they here, and as worthily. And this is not onely found in the Engliſh and Welch, but in all other languages, to be moſt ridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous: and yet no Grammar prouideth for this miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefe, nor indeed can it prouide, vnleſſe euery na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſhould make ſo many ſeueral Grammars of one and the ſame tongue, as there are ſeuerall ſorts of nations to communicate with it: which were a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry great and a voluminous inconvenience.</p>
            <p>Againe, in ſuch members, wherein two ſeuerall tongues may place theſe peeces of ſpeech alike, ſo that euery peece of the one be anſwerable to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:20235:6"/>peece of the other, both in place and ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation: the whole member put together in the one and the other tongue, ſhall be good &amp; perfect ſenſe in the one, and no way vnderſtood in the other lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage. For though the words thereof be all, by both tongues acknowledged; yet being put toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, the one of theſe nations receiues, the other diſclaimes the member: which is manifeſt between the Engliſh and the Italian. For, though <hi>un</hi> be an; <hi>cavallo,</hi> horſe; <hi>di,</hi> of; <hi>buon,</hi> good; <hi>metallo,</hi> metall: and <hi>[An horſe of good metall]</hi> put together be good En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh; yet the Italian vnderſtands not <hi>vn cavallo di buon metallo</hi> to be Italian, but diſclaimes it. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doth any Grammar remedy this particular, nor indeede can remedy it, vnleſſe it draw all the proprieties of euery language of the world, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply them to it ſelfe in and for euery different lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage; which would proue a greater inconveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence then the former. If therefore we would not (with Art) fall vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> theſe deformities of miſpeccing and miſmembring languages, we muſt rely wholy vpon Authoritie, from whence, euen Art her ſelfe was drawne, though inſufficient; and to which, when Art can ſay no more, ſhe oft referrs vs. Now if this Authoritie be ſo reduced by Analyſis to pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe, that we neither teare in peeces, or breake the members of ſpeech, nor hurt the ioynts or wheeles on which it runneth: and then be made vp a new compoſition or method of writing after mine in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention; it ſhall not onely demonſtrate the poſſibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie of a way to learne this better Latin, (and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by aſſure you that I can be as good as my promiſe)
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:20235:7"/>but it ſhall alſo (as I haue ſaid in mine <hi>Appeale</hi>) giue any man a reall power of writing rightly the firſt day he ſets vpon it. But, vnderſtand me, this power is in my books, and not in his braines that writeth, till he by dayly practiſe haue reduced this power of my books to an habit in himſelfe. And no doubt but an habit may this way in halfe the time be got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, that is ſpent in Grammar. And then, our habit is made in Latine-Latine, the other in Grammar-Latine; the differences whereof haue formerly been debated. Neither ſhall wee in this <hi>Latine-Latine</hi> ſtand in need of rules of conſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (which Gram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mars for the moſt part giue) or poſition and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prietie (which they giue not;) for theſe fall all in ſenſe and meaning, wherein all the members and clauſes of all Languages haue their meetings.</p>
            <p>But they continue to obiect,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> that Authoritie cannot affoord members for all ſenſes.</p>
            <p>To this I anſwer, that ſenſes, clauſes or members, conſiſt as well in forme as in matter. In forme, they are all in Authoritie; otherwiſe Art had not found them, being onely produced from Authoritie; and therefore they occurre in my method out of Authors. In matter they are alſo the moſt part there, excepting ſome few names of things that fell not within the diſcourſes of mine Authors; or haue ſince their times been invented; and theſe ſhall be affoorded by ſupplement, which is alſo drawne out of authoritie. And therefore <hi>I craue leaue to print theſe Authors with this ſupplement,</hi> which ſome haue thought that I had neuer dreamed of, but vpon their obiections made within theſe twelue months:
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:20235:7"/>whereas I haue good teſtimonie of the thing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun and almoſt halfe done aboue theſe ſix yeares. Moreouer, euery ſenſe may in one and the ſame tongue be many wayes altered in the words or clau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and yet produce alwayes the ſelfe ſame mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning. Now, as euery tongue hath this varietie; ſo any, or euery one of theſe varieties is not onely a due expreſſion of that ſenſe in one and the ſame tongue, but alſo of all and euery particular varia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of that ſenſe in euery other language. Other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe the Poet ſhould not be able to expreſſe him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe Poetically both in other numbers and other frames &amp; formes of ſpeech than are vſuall amongſt Orators: nor could Orators giue vs their meanings now in an humble, now in a loftie, now in a middle, or other kindes or ſtyles of writing. And yet euery one of theſe can produce, after his owne maner, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery thing that may be ſpoken; witneſſe the Poets
<q>Quicquid conabor dicere verſus erit.</q> And conſidering that all theſe wayes of expreſſion fall within the limits of mine inſtrument, either by authoritie or ſupplement, I cannot ſo much as dreame of an impoſſibilitie of producing any thing that may be ſpoken.</p>
            <p>Hereupon they further demaund,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> Where are theſe Authors reduced to your method? and where that ſupplement? vnleſſe you produce them (ſay they) you will neither be beleeued, nor get your licence.</p>
            <p>This were but hard meaſure (ſaid I) conſidering ſo many preſidents to the contrary. There was a Patent, and an Act of Parliament paſſed before
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:20235:8"/>the bringing of the New-riuer water from <hi>Ware</hi> to <hi>London;</hi> and the like for cutting the paſſage of a riuer from <hi>Tame</hi> to <hi>Oxford.</hi> Now, if men that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended good but to ſome parts of priuate Cities, be thus fauoured; it is not likely that I (that pleade for euery mans poſteritie, yea his, what ere he be, that's moſt againſt me; as alſo in the behalfe of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny nations and whole kingdomes, and for thoſe Authors that they ſo much deſire and reuerence) ſhould be driuen to hazard both time, labour, and expences, without ſome kind of aſſurance as well from his Maieſtie as the Parliament, that I ſhall not ruine both my ſelfe and others which haue herein ayded me. Epecially conſidering how apt men are now adayes to ſnatch the bread out of other mens mouthes, and to ſell their labours to their owne profits, and grow fat vpon them, while thoſe that ſweat and groned to produce them, periſh with fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine. Which ofteneſt happens to poore ſtudents, who are contented to be giuen to vnderſtand, that it is enough for them to haue the honour of their books, in lieu of their labour, time and charges: and in the meane ſeaſon are laught at, as fooliſh Logi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians that will loſe the ſubſtance for ſo poore an accident. But admit yet farther, that after priui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge granted, I ſhould not be able to performe what I intended; there's no mans reputation, no mans time, labour and expences lies at ſtake but mine. So that if I performe, it was well granted; in that euery man ſhall reape the benefit: if I perform not, yet was it well granted; in that it turnes to my iuſt puniſhment: and therefore in my opinion I
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:20235:8"/>ſhould not be vrged to a greater inconvenience, (as to beſtow yet other foure or fiue hundred pounds) to produce that, which when it is produced, giues me no more aſſurance of a priuiledge, then at this preſent.</p>
            <p>Then was it obiected,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> that his Maieſtie had al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>readie confirmed a Patent granted for the Gram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mar, and would admit of no other courſe of teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
            <p>Whereupon I demanded, what hinderance the Goldſmiths priuiledge was to the Braſiers. I deſire not the ſuppreſſion or hinderance of Grammar, but the puritie of Latine. Againe, this Grammar was priuiledged to forbid all other Grammars: but I ſeeke not to introduce another Grammar, except we ſhall very improperly call it <hi>Cicero's Grammar.</hi> My deſire is only, that ſuch as are weary, and would not, or can no longer go by Grammar, or are not deſirous of Grammar-Latine, might be admitted to an eaſie and profitable vſe of Authors, and to theſe Authors own way of teaching their own lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage without Grammar; as being two ſundry courſes, to two diuers ends. For Authors cannot bring a man to Grammar-Latine, nor Grammars vnto Authors Latine, as is proued. Nay further, I find the Preface it ſelfe to this priuiledged Gram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mar, to be more fauourable on my behalfe then this opinion: for it ſayes plainly, that <hi>it is not amiſse, if one ſeeing by triall an eaſier and readier way than the common ſort of teachers do, would ſay what he hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, and for the commodity allowed; that other not know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſame, might by experience proue the like, and
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:20235:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>then by proofe reaſonably iudge the like: not excluding [by this priuiledged Grammar] the better way when it is found out, but in the meane ſeaſon forbidding the worſe.</hi> Now, I hauing by triall proued this way by Authors, to be another, and an eaſier and readier way than that of Grammar, and allowing thereof for the infinite commoditie that I finde therein, humbly intreate that I may be priuiledged to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce my bookes, that may make others proue and iudge as I doe; according to the intent of the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alledged Preface.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> What proofe, ſay they, or demonſtration, can you bring vs of this way of yours?</p>
            <p>I anſwered, a two-fold proofe: one, of a power that theſe bookes bring to any man, the firſt day to write rightly by them: And another, of this power, reduced by an exerciſe to an habit of wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting rightly without them. Of the firſt kind (in that this method holdeth in all Languages as well as in Latine) take this Italian Letter, tranſlated by a Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlewoman that knowes not two words of that lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, and that, the firſt day that ſhe applied her ſelfe vnto it.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="ita">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Fratello mio cariſsimo.</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Quantu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>que mi paia di poter eſſer piu che certo, che tutti gli uffici li quali ho fatto per te, ti ſono ſtati gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſsimi: &amp; che queſta fu la cagione, che tu mi hai ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duto piu che non havevi riceuuto: nondimeno. perche veggo nelle tue lettere, che tu hai qualch'ambra di me, ſon conſtretto a giuſtificarmi con teco: Perioche, il pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo di Gennaio, ho voluto intier amente farti paleſe l'a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimo mio, &amp; diogni coſa ti darei conto particolare, ma
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:20235:9"/>che il conſiglio non mi pareva punto noceſſario, poten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doſi torcere quello, che con ſincera mente è ſtato ſcritto, a ſentimento contrario. Laonde, ſe tu mi ami all'uſato, baſta quello ch'io ſcriſsi. Io non poſſo eſſer piu voſtro che mi ſia. Ec mi vi raccomando.</hi> 
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>Di Londra a <date>li 10. <hi>de Decembre.</hi> 1620.</date>
                     </dateline>
                     <signed>Di V. S. Fratello aff<hi rend="sup">mo</hi>. <hi>N.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>Of the ſame kinde is this other in Latine, tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated out of Engliſh, through power giuen in my bookes, to a capable yong man, that had been ſix yeares at a Grammar Schoole, and had diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued eighteen moneths.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="lat">
               <body>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Non qui parum habet, ſed qui plus cupit, pauper eſt. Ad hoc enim multis illi rebus opus eſt; ad illud, tantum animo ſano, &amp; erecto, deſpiciente fortunam. Sed, quem mihi dabis, cui quantulumcunque ſupereſt, ſat eſt? Si volueris attendere; ad manum eſt quod ſat eſt: ſed, niſi ſapienti ſua non placent. Adhuc, concipere animo non potes, quam ſic ſe contentus, qui fictilibus ſic vtitur, quemaamodum argento: ſed, oum puerilem animum de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſueris, &amp;, te in viros Philoſophia tranſcripſerit, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligas ſapientem ſe ipſo eſſe contentum, &amp; hominem tam bene culmo quam auro tegi. Sed vt epiſtolae finem imponam; mihi crede, Non eſt beatus, eſſe ſe qui non pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tat. Haec, &amp; huiuſmodi verſanda in animo ſunt, vt tibi conting at vera libertas, &amp; vt poſsis aequo animo vitam relinquere. Vale.</hi>
                  </p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>But, becauſe I was deſirous to ſee how well hee could tranſlate it of himſelfe, without the power giuen him by theſe books, I made him firſt make it in his owne Latine, which (with ſome help of ſuch
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:20235:10"/>as had done it before him) was as followeth:
<q>Iſte non eſt pauper qui parum habet, ſed qui plus appetit. Nam huic multa deſunt; illi, animo ſolum integro, &amp; e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recto, fortunâ diſpicientiâ. Sed, quiſnam, qui contentus eſt rebus ſuis: Si enim in mentem tuam benè introſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cias, ſatis adeſt; ſed nulli preter ſapientes placati aut contenti ſunt eo quod habent. Adhuc enim in animo non ſorbeas, quàm contentus eſt ſemitipſo qui vaſibus fictilibus vtitur vice toreumatis; Sed cum animum puerilem deponas, &amp; Philoſophia in numeros hominum te referat, inuenies quod hominem eſt aeque culmene te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctum quam aurum. Sed vt literam concludam (crede mihi) hominem iſtum non eſse beatum quem ſeipſum it a eſſe non cogitat. Hec &amp; ſimilia ſepe ſunt ad cogitanda vt veram libertatem paras &amp; vitam tuam libenter linqueres.</q>
            </p>
            <p>In verſe alſo, theſe are of that firſt kind, made by men of great iudgement, who were deſirous to make ſome proofe thereof.</p>
            <q>Ignarus facti cecini ſine lumine carmen.</q>
            <p>And this Diſtichon, made vpon this following Engliſh: <hi>Without ſenſe or reaſon a thing promiſed cannot be beleeued.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>Promiſsis adhibere fidem ſine lumine ſenſus,</l>
               <l>Aut mentis, levit as creditur ingenij.</l>
            </q>
            <p>By <hi>the ſecond way,</hi> that is, by the power of thoſe bookes, reduced by a moneths practiſe to the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of an habit, theſe exerciſes were made without thoſe bookes.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="lat">
               <body>
                  <head>In the Latin of <hi>Seneca.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Si aliquem amicum exiſtimas (mi Philippe) qui nuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:20235:10"/>eſt, quia vbique est; vehementer erras. Nam, aegri animi iſta iactatio eſt. Nihil aequè ſanitatem impedit, quam remedior um crebra mutatio. Nec coaleſcit verae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amicitiae planta, quae ſaepè transfertur. Itaque, diu cogi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta, an tibi in amicitiam aliquis recipiendus ſit. Ante ami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citiam iudicandum, Sed, cum placuerit fieri, cum amico omnes curas omnes cogitationes tuas miſce. Nam, multi fallere docueruat dum timent falli. Vale.</hi>
                  </p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="lat">
               <body>
                  <head>In <hi>Caeſars</hi> Latin.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Vbi per exploratores Henricus certior factus eſt, Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis eſſe in animo, eum rapinis populationibuſ<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> prohibere; non expectandum ſibi ſtatuit. Qua de cauſa, maturat ab agro Bononienſium proficiſci. Et quam maximis itine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribus poteſt in Normandiam vlteriorem contendit, &amp; ad Rothomagum per venit. Pontem iubet reſcindi: A Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quana, ad montem Sanctae Katharinae, millia paſſuum novem, murum, in altitudinem pedum ſexdecim, foſſam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que perduit. Galli iam per fines Picardorum ſuas co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pias traduxerant, &amp; in Normannorum fines pervene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant. Henricus negat ſe poſſe iter ulli per Normandiam dare. Et, ſi vim facere conentur, prohibiturum oſtendit. Poſtero die, caſtra ex eo loco movent, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="lat">
               <body>
                  <head>In <hi>Cicero's</hi> Epiſtolatorie Latin.</head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Amantiſsime amice,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Noſtris rationibus maximé conducere videtur, plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rimos noſtros amicos inveniri: quoniam videtur in ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fragijs multum poſſe aduerſarius noſter. A vunculus tuus obſervat Cancellarium maximè: ſed, fuit &amp; mihi &amp; Edvardo fratri magno vſui. Cum à Iudicijs forum re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frixerit, ſcribam ad te: vides enim, quod adhuc con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iectura prouideri poſsit, in quo curſu ſumus. Multum te amamus. Sed, abs te peto vt mihi hoc ignoſcas. Vale.</hi>
                  </p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:20235:11"/>
            <p> The like may be done in the Latine of other an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient or moderne Authors, as of <hi>Livie, Plinie, Taci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus,</hi> or of <hi>Lipſius,</hi> or any other whatſoeuer: and that not onely (as is ſaid) in Latine, but in euery other language alſo.</p>
            <p>But we vnderſtand,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="9"/> ſay they, that in this way of yours by Authors, you would haue theſe clau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, which you ſpeake of, to be rendred whole: which cannot ſinke into our heads to be good, by reaſon that you know not, by this means, what the words do ſignifie: and therefore it were much bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that euery clauſe ſhould be conſtrued word for word. And beſides, to take whole clauſes out of Authors, were to ſteale.</p>
            <p>Whereunto I anſwered: Firſt, you may by triall find, that this conſtruing word for word, is altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther impoſſible in any language: Next, you may ſee the inconvenience thereof by the French-mans Engliſh: for while he followes the correſpondence of words, he forgets their placing; and therefore ſaith, <hi>I you pray Sir,</hi> placing our Engliſh as his <hi>Ie vous prie Monſieur</hi> is placed, which is abſurd and barbarous; and proceedeth onely from his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruing word for word; euery man applying the words of a forreine language according as they are ranged in his owne. Wherfore I had rather a ſcho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar ſhould remember the naturall and receiued po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of a clauſe by keeping the words alwayes all together, than vnderſtand the particular correſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of the words, and thereby loſe their proper places. For diſcretion, and compariſon of clauſe with clauſe, will at length bring the vnderſtanding
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:20235:11"/>of the words, whether we will or no; but nothing will bring the true poſition of theſe words againe, by reaſon that our owne tongue doth therein ſtill miſguide vs, and makes vs alwayes to be diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed for ſtrangers, euen in our very writing. And the maineſt reaſon thereof is this, that clauſes are almoſt of the ſame condition that words are. For, as out of words of 2.3.4. or 5. letters, there may be 2.6.24. or 120. various reuolutions, and yet but one of thoſe variations ſhall be allotted to ſignifie this or that one thing in particular: So is it in clauſes of 2.3.4. or 5. words, whoſe variations may be as many as was before ſaid of the letters; yet vſe hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly made choice but of one of thoſe reuolutions of words to ſtand for this or that ſenſe: which if you preciſely take not, without adding, diminiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing or tranſpoſing; you either alter the ſenſe, maner of ſtyle, or dialect; or elſe you ſpeake a kind of non ſenſe. And that clauſe or ſenſe, that vſe hath taken hold of in one language, ſhall not many times haue the ſelfe ſame number of words in another; and therefore you muſt faile of your verball tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation: and in thoſe that haue the ſelfe ſame num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, you ſeldome finde the words that ſignifie and expreſſe each other, to haue in both tongues the ſame poſition. Wherfore, if you take not the whole clauſe together in the one and the other tongue, you muſt at ſome time ſpeake barbarouſly of neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie. Now if this be that, which you call theft or ſtealing, there are none of vs that fall not hourely within the compaſſe of this kind of theevery. For, if you marke it wel, all ſpeech runnes in this maner,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:20235:12"/>and euery man ſpeakes each others clauſes. True it is, that one and the ſame clauſe or ſenſe, may (as I haue ſaid) be diuers wayes deliuered; but then you keep not the ſame words or number of them, but vary <hi>per Synonomiam, Enallagen, Antonomaſiam, Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riphraſin, Metaphoram,</hi> and other ſuch like variati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; which all muſt alſo keepe their receiued clauſes, or elſe we ſhall do wrong to languages.</p>
            <p>Other demaunds and obiections leſſe materiall, as not touching the thing it ſelfe, but ſome particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar and by-reſpects, would cloy your eares with more then becomes a modeſt brevitie: wherefore leauing them, till ſome farther occaſion offered; and moſt humbly intreating you to caſt a fauoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble eye on this Petition. I in all obedience dedicate my ſelfe, my labour, and the reſt of my life, in the full extent of my whole talent, to the eternall glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of my God, to the loyall ſervice I owe vnto my Soueraigne and his Succeſſion, and to the future good of you and your poſteritie.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:20235:12"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
